Today's דף daf is כ"ה. chaf-hey. We pick up on כ"ד עמוד
ב' chaf-daled amud bet at the two dots, and we're at the
section of the משנה Mishna where discussing לשמה lishmah and the part
that says that a person cannot write open-ended, write for wife number
one or write for one wife and I'll decide which wife to
use it for. And then the גמרא Gemara had a discussion about
the fact that well, it sounds like you can write it for
the intent for a specific wife even with the same names, and
what does that tell you about the need for a שטר? shtar?
Doesn't the שטר shtar have to be evident who it's referring to?
And said, well, you know, maybe it is evident based on which
wife is holding it, and that seemed to be a pretty reasonable
position. Although in the end, the גמרא Gemara said, well, maybe we
have to be talking according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer where the
idea of the גט get serving as a שטר ראיה shtar re'ayah
as also testimony is not necessarily an essential part and that there
are עדי מסירה. adei mesirah. Okay, so that was interesting because again,
you could have said that even if there are people with similar
names, it all gets clarified based on the person holding the גט.
get. Anyway, now the גמרא Gemara continues and it says like this.
It is about eight lines from the bottom, seven lines from the
bottom. אמר רב כולם פוסלין לכהונה חוץ מן הראשון. Amar Rav: Kulam
poslin lakehunah chutz min harishon. So all these גיטין gittin which are
not good because they're not לשמה, lishmah, the question is what happens
if they were given anyway? A person wrote a גט get שלא
לשמה, shelo lishmah, but the names are right. So on the surface,
it looked good. The problem is completely non-visible, right?
It was what was going on in the head of the person
who was writing it. So does that create a problem? If that
גט get was given, it creates the impression that this woman was
divorced, because everything that's observable looks totally fine. And does that therefore
make her מדרבנן miderabbanan פסול לכהונה, pasul lakehunah, which is like the
worst of both worlds? You're not divorced, but because it looks like
you're divorced, if you're, you know, you'll be considered a גרושה grusha
for a כהן. kohen. So if your husband dies now and you're
an אלמנה, almanah, it doesn't matter, you're also a גרושה grusha for
a כהן. kohen.
What let's say I was just נמלך nimlach and I never gave
it to her and, you know, and the שליח shaliach was there?
Right, so that's going to be a range of questions, which type
of גיטין gittin would fall into this category. Right now we're talking
about in the context of this משנה, Mishna, but you could raise
it about any פסול pasul גט. get. But again, what makes this
משנה Mishna one that particularly you might think it's relevant is because
the problem here is completely not visible from the גט get and
the way the גט get was given. It's all in the secret
background about why, not whatever, you know what I mean? Or is
in the mind of the סופר sofer when it was being written.
So that's a particular point. Now, of course, if it's פסול מן
הכהונה pasul min hakehunah and she's married to a כהן, kohen, right?
So then it's, so that's what רש"י Rashi says, אם בעלה כהן
נפסלה עליו משום גרושה. im ba'alah kohen nifselah alav mishum grusha.
So not only is it if her husband dies, now she's אסור
asur to a כהן, kohen, if her husband is a כהן, kohen,
gave her this גט, פסול get pasul, גט, get, and now he
changed his mind, it's too bad. Okay, you're already considered to be
a גרושה grusha and she can't
continue to live with a כהן. kohen. Now he must divorce her.
Right. So I guess that's the good side of it, is that
at least we're going to if the divorce was the right thing,
we're going to force, but okay. But the point is, that's the
question. Now, this is called in a certain סוגיא sugya ריח הגט.
rei'ach haget. It smells like a גט. get, If it walks like
a גט get. and it talks like a גט get and it
smells like a גט. get But if it smells like a גט,
get. are we going to consider her to be מדרבנן miderabbanan a
גרושה? grusha? So, so that is the first statement, כולם פסולים חוץ
מן הראשון. Kulam psulim chutz min harishon.
The only one that wouldn't be is the גט get, that was
written as a, you know, in the סופר sofer school, when it's
written not even for the purpose of גיטין. gittin. That, it's too
obvious to people that this is, like again, it's not visible physically
in the גט, get but that was never treated as a גט.
get, That was something that was purely just done as a practice.
Okay, and there we're not going
to.
Wait, for an outside observer, like? I understand.
I was underscoring the outside observer, you know, the גמרא Gemara to
help you understand why we would create this idea of ריח הגט.
rei'ach haget. Okay, but if that's your only criteria, then it doesn't
make a sense to distinguish. What he's saying is, you know, the
context, people know, oh yeah, you know, somehow there'll be a context
that people will know if something was written only as practice. Okay,
but if it was at one time treated with the weight of
a גט get. written by one guy and now another guy is
using it, that's too much of a problem. חוץ מן הראשון. chutz
min harishon.
What if
the woman would say she doesn't want that, she wants a גט
get that's going to be acceptable in all situations?
Yeah, I mean, if her husband the כהן, kohen, we would force
her to accept a, I mean, you know, we would force him
to give her a גט get after this because now she's considered
a
גרושה מדרבנן. grusha miderabbanan. If the guy is just להכעיס, lehach'is, one
wonders what would he be able to do this להכעיס, lehach'is, write
her this פסול pasul גט, get give it to her, so then
after he says after I die I want to make sure you're
as miserable even after I'm dead, so I'm going to give you
a גט get, that you can't marry a כהן kohen after I
die or something like that. I don't know. Anyway, but who knows?
Okay, but that's his position. כולם פסולים חוץ מן הראשון. Kulam psulim
chutz min harishon. ושמואל אמר אף ראשון נמי פוסל. u'shmuel amar af
rishon nami posel. So שמואל Shmuel says, no, all of them create
a problem because of the reason I said. It all looks כשר,
kasher, so therefore they're all going to create a problem. ואזל שמואל
לטעמיה, ve'azal Shmuel leta'amei, שמואל Shmuel goes to
his... Now he doesn't say just by this where, as I said,
visibly it all looks okay. Whenever there's a גט get that's פסול,
pasul okay, or whenever they use the phrase גט פסול, get pasul,
okay,
גט get פסול, pasul, פסול ופוסל. pasul u'poseil. It's invalid, but it
invalidates her and makes her considered a גרושה. grusha. Now Rambam for
example in הלכות גיטין, Hilchos Gittin, Rambam you got to love Rambam,
he is so systematic, right? and precise. And he says I'm going
to use the term פסול pasul when I am referring to something
that's rabbinically a problem. And I'm going to use the word בטל
batel for a גט get when it's דאורייתא de'oraisa a problem, okay?
So this, so for, anyway and the, now the גמרא Gemara is
not that consistent. But you know שמואל Shmuel might be saying if
sometimes it says like אין לגרש בו בטל הרי זה גט בטל,
ein le'gareish bo batel harei zeh get batel, right,
then that might mean like it's so off the boat the board
that it's not a problem. That's completely you know out of the
category. But פסול pasul you know is not as wrong of a
language, which means that it still doesn't seem as completely bad. And
therefore that language for שמואל Shmuel it's not clear if he's saying
דאורייתא de'oraisa versus דרבנן de'rabbanan or what he's saying, but that language
of פסול pasul signals to you that it's still is enough of
a problem that it's going to make her a גרושה. grusha. It's
not כשר גט, kosher get, might even be פסול דאורייתא, pasul de'oraisa,
right? I mean presumably it is בטל דאורייתא. batel de'oraisa. If it
was only a דרבנן de'rabbanan problem she obviously would be פסול לכהונה.
pasul l'kehuna. Okay so it might be that it's not a good
גט דאורייתא get de'oraisa but it looks enough like of an issue
that she's going to be פסול לכהונה. pasul l'kehuna. So
כל מקום ששנו חכמים גט פסול, kol makom sheshanu chachamim get pasul,
what they're telling you is פסול ופוסל. pasul u'poseil. If they say
חליצה פסולה, chalitza psula, a חליצה chalitza done in the wrong way
and they use the phrase פסולה, psula, what they mean by that
phrase פסולה psula is פסולה ופוסלתה. psula u'posaltah. Same thing. It's not
a good חליצה chalitza but now she is considered to be already
a חלוצה. chaluza. For what purpose? פוסלתה מן האחים. posaltah min ha'achim.
You could say that if he dies she's now אסורה לכהונה assura
l'kehuna okay like a גרושה, grusha, חלוצה אסורה לכהונה. chaluza assura l'kehuna.
But what he also says is when one brother does חליצה chalitza
the other brothers can't do יבום yibum afterwards. So if one brother
does a פסול חליצה, pasul chalitza, she's no longer eligible for a
יבום yibum with the brother. Okay so שמואל Shmuel says that term
always means that it's on the one hand no, it's the worst
of both worlds, it's no good, but we treat it like it's
good to create problems. Okay.
במערבא אמרי משמיה דרבי אליעזר, Bemarava amri mishmei de'Rabbi Eliezer, in מערבא
Marava they say in the name of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, שמאל
ולילה פסולה smol velaila psula by this by חליצה. chalitza. No, by
חליצה. chalitza. If a guy did a חליצה chalitza right with his
left hand okay, or no you know what we're not dealing with
הלכות יבום Hilchos Yibum so let's just deal with not not explore
that, or he did it at night and חליצה chalitza is supposed
to be done during the day okay,
or with her left foot I guess it's also could be the
שמאל. smol. I think it's more her left foot, excuse me.
Wait a minute what does she have to do with her left
foot or right
foot?
I'm sorry I'm sorry I'm sorry I'm sorry right. She's the one
who I'm sorry I got
confused. It's too early for me. She does the חליצה chalitza with
his left foot right? With his right foot I mean she's supposed
to with his right foot. Thank you. Okay anyway let's do that
again. Okay. במערבא אמרי משמיה דרבי אליעזר. Bemarava amri mishmei de'Rabbi Eliezer.
שמאל ולילה smol velaila if she took it off thank you she
took it off of his left foot okay rather than his right
foot because it's supposed to be on his right foot the shoe.
She took off the shoe from his left foot or she did
it at night okay פסולות ופוסלות. psulos u'poslos.
Those are invalid חליצות chalitzos but then they are enough
problematic that they make her no longer eligible for the brothers. Okay.
What do you mean by problematic? What?
I don't know but we're not dealing with it. Okay. קטן ואנפיליא
Katan ve'anpilya however if it was a minor who was doing the
חליצה chalitza okay or it was a slipper that was being used
and not a shoe so that's more obviously problem because the פסוק
pasuk says איש ish so it's more obvious that a קטן katan
is no good and it says נעלו na'alo so it's more obviously
that a slipper doesn't count as a shoe. So those things פסולות
ואין פוסלות. psulos ve'ein poslos. Are so obviously a problem that they
while they are not a legitimate חליצה chalitza they don't make her
forbidden either. Okay so basically you have the irony right that if
something that is a bigger problem more obvious more evident of a
problem is in the end is nothing, it's like nothing happened, whereas
something that is not valid but is more of what we would
call in the פרשה parsha looks more כשר, kosher, is less obviously
פסול, pasul, that creates more problems because it creates an impression. So
you could have that by a גט get and that's called a
ריח הגט reiach haget okay when a גט get looks כשר kosher
and that would still make her considered to be a גרושה מדרבנן
grusha mi'de'rabbanan okay and you could have it by a חליצה chalitza
which also it looks כשר kosher or it's you know the פסול
psul isn't as self-evident. So where do you draw the line? Okay
so one approach wanted to limit it like I wanted to say
to the cases of the משנה Mishna which basically the... Problem was
not at all visible, the לשמה lishma problem. Here you're getting cases
which are much broader to include according to שמואל Shmuel anytime it
uses the word פסול psul or פסולה, psula, it means that it
creates a problem, okay, that it makes her מדרבנן miderabanan a גרושה,
gerusha, מדרבנן miderabanan a חלוצה. chalutza. And in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
they didn't have a כלל, klal, they wanted to look case by
case and they said something which is maybe explicit in the פסוק
pasuk is not a problem. Something that's less explicit in the פסוק,
pasuk, okay, that does create a problem because that does, it's not
as obvious that it's invalid. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues,
marry at all or not at all?
No, well, she can marry if she gets after she gets a
good חליצה. chalitza.
You mean then she still has to get a good one?
Yeah, all these cases presumably are פסול דאורייתא, psul d'Oraita, דאורייתא d'Oraita
it's not a good גט, get, דאורייתא d'Oraita it's not a good
חליצה. chalitza. So דאורייתא d'Oraita really she should be completely like nothing
happened, but because it looks enough like something happened, cases which the
do look like something happened, מדרבנן miderabanan they give her that status
and then she's in the worst of both worlds.
So who gives the חליצה chalitza then? That same husband's brother has
to redo it?
Right,
she's qualified the other brothers for ייבום yibum because the other brothers
do the חליצה chalitza again, that's an interesting question. That I don't
know, that's an interesting question. Okay, yeah.
So let me understand, like let's say, you know, בעלה, ba'ala, right,
then he was PA, I'm talking about the man, the married case?
Right. So obviously he didn't want to give the גט, get, but
now because the גט's get there and it's got פסול psul and
now she actually has to get divorced? That's kind of ironic.
No, no, no, it's all this is when a גט get is
given. It's not the physical presence of a גט. get. It's when
the גט get was given, so it looks like she was divorced.
Okay, now זעירי אמר כולם אין פוסלין חוץ מן האחרונה. Zeiri amar
kulan ein poslin chutz min ha'achrona. זעירי Zeiri is much more limited.
The only case that is a problem of this ריח הגט reiach
haget that it's not only not good but we'll treat her as
if she's מגורשת megureshet because it looks like it might be good
is the last case. The last case, remember, is he has two
wives with the same name and he says, "I'll decide which one
I want to divorce." Okay, so that case he says, first of
all, it's very rare, two wives with the same name. Second of
all, that case is the one that is the most that looks
like it could be kosher. It wasn't written for somebody else, it
was left open-ended. That's the only problem of ריח הגט. reiach haget.
Nothing else is ריח הגט. reiach haget. Anything else that's פסול psul
is פסול, psul, we do not put this woman into this limbo
status. Okay, so וכן אמר רב אסי כולם אין פוסלין חוץ מן
האחרונה. v'chen amar Rav Assi kulan ein poslin chutz min ha'achrona. The
only thing that creates a problem that looks kosher enough to create
a problem is the last case. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar,
God bless רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, אף אחרונה נמי אינו פוסל. af
achrona nami eino posel. Okay, even the last one. Like, no, if
it's not a good גט, get, it's not a good גט, get,
end of story. We do not sort of, you know, create this
middle state that you're that it's good enough for you to be
ספק safek for you to be מדרבנן מגורשת miderabanan megureshet and create
all the problems but not treat her to be really divorced. It's
not a גט, get, it's not a גט, get, end of story.
אף האחרון נמי אינו פוסל. af ha'achron nami eino posel. ואזל רבי
יוחנן לטעמיה, v'azal Rabbi Yochanan l'taameih, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan goes according
to his reasoning, דאמר רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן האחים שחלקו לקוחות
הן ומחזירין זה לזה ביובל. d'amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan ha'achim
shechalku lakochot hen umachzirin zeh lazeh b'Yovel. Now, it's very funny why
the גמרא Gemara says ואזל רבי יוחנן לטעמיה v'azal Rabbi Yochanan l'taameih
because nobody is debating that the last case is פסול, psul, but
it's just telling you that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan really rejects this
idea of ברירה. breira. Right, remember the last case, "I'll decide which
wife I want to give it to," in a way it's a
type of a ברירה. breira. Can I leave something open-ended, decide later,
and then retroactively it'll define what happened earlier? Now the גמרא Gemara
thinks that that idea of ברירה breira is also relevant to this
case of how do we envision what it means when somebody dies
and the and brothers inherit the estate? Okay, because a person dies
and he leaves this undifferentiated estate to all the brothers. Then they
come and they divvy it up. You get the house, I'll get
the car, you get this, I'll get that or whatever. Okay, so
what did that mean? Does it mean it went to a state
where it was communally owned and then it was the partnership, as
it was, was dissolved? Okay, and if that's true, if we're dissolving
a partnership, basically what I'm saying to you is, I'll give you
your portion, my portion in the house, if you give me your
portion in the in, you know, in the in, you know,
in the car. Okay, not really a fair trade, but whatever, I
like the Jaguar, so we're going to do it. Okay, fine. So,
okay, so anyway, it's a run-down house. Okay,
so that's what it would mean if it was a partnership, we
all owned 50 percent, let's say there's just two of us, we
both own 50 percent in everything and I'll swap my portion in
X for your portion in Z. Okay, that's how one way of
conceiving what happens when it goes from communally held to divided. But
if you held יש ברירה, yesh breira, you would say once we
make up whatever mind we make up, then it turns out that
in hindsight we say, "Oh, now we get
it, you inherited the house and I inherited the car." It's that
how
retroactively determines what was the what was the part of the estate
each one of us was meant to inherit. Okay, now obviously it's
a different type of a יש ברירה. yesh breira. ברירה breira is
easier when you stipulate explicitly from the beginning. Okay, I am going
to writing this for the wife who will be determined later. I
am separating תרומות ומעשרות trumot u'maasrot now from which grain, the grain...
The grain I will identify later. So you are saying now and
the blank gets filled in. Here the guy just died, nobody said
anything, and we're just going to assert a type of determinism that
based on what later decisions get made, if you live in a
deterministic world then we'll say retroactively it shows that was the part
of the estate you were always going to get. That's a type
of a יש ברירה, yesh bereirah, okay? So that's the question of
how do you look at inheritance. So if you look at it
as an אין ברירה ein bereirah way, that basically we hold it
communally and we bought each other's portion off, okay, then essentially I
have purchased part of your car and you purchased part of my
house. So האחין שחלקו לקוחות הן, ha'achin shechalaku lekuchot hen, brothers after
they divide the estate are considered to have purchased from one another,
bought each other off from their portion. What's the relevance of that?
ומחזירין זה לזה ביובל. umachzirin zeh lazeh beyovel. Okay, so basically we
had a nice house in תל אביב Tel Aviv and a nice
house in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. I took the ירושלים Yerushalayim house, you took
the תל אביב Tel Aviv house. So basically we purchased half of
each other's house, right? So now comes the יובל. yovel. What does
the יובל yovel say? If you purchased real estate, right, comes the
יובל, yovel, it all goes back to the original owner. Well, the
original owner is this abstract entity called the estate. So comes the
יובל, yovel, now our houses go back to the estate ownership and
if we wanted to split it again, we'd split it again, but
now you have a choice to make a different decision or whatever,
right? So that would be the idea if you viewed them as
אין ברירה ein bereirah and they purchased from one another. If you
say יש ברירה, yesh bereirah, nobody purchased anything. I always inherited the
ירושלים Yerushalayim house and you always inherited the תל אביב Tel Aviv
house. יובל yovel isn't going to do anything to that. So רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says אין ברירה ein bereirah and ומחזירין זה לזה
ביובל. umachzirin zeh lazeh beyovel. So the גמרא gemara says, "Ah, so
he's consistent, because our משנה mishnah also holds אין ברירה," ein bereirah,
okay, because our משנה mishnah also holds you can't determine which wife
it is after the fact. The problem is nobody disagrees with the
משנה. mishnah. The question is, is there an issue of ריח הגט?
rei'ach hagget? Does it smell bad enough or problematic enough? And it
seems like what the גמרא gemara is saying is that if normally
you hold יש ברירה, yesh bereirah, but you say that in our
משנה mishnah it doesn't work because there's a special לשמה lishmah requirement,
so even ברירה bereirah doesn't work because the תורה Torah says לשמה
lishmah and you have to know concretely when you are writing it
who you're having in mind, and it can't be determined later. But
if in general you hold יש ברירה, yesh bereirah, then it still
looks like a problem, right? Because in general that type of a
stipulation would work. So that would be a ריח הגט rei'ach hagget
problem. But רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
who always says אין ברירה, ein bereirah, okay, for רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan it's obvious that even the last case of the משנה mishnah
is not a problem and therefore it's not a ריח הגט. rei'ach
hagget. And therefore it's complete—you understand the issue here? ריח הגט, rei'ach
hagget, nobody disagrees that it's invalid. The question is does it look
possibly kosher enough that we מדרבנן miderabbanan treat her as מגורשת megureshet
and create a problem of ריח הגט? rei'ach hagget? So גמרא gemara
says רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says even the last one is not
a problem and גמרא gemara says he's consistent. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
in general says אין ברירה, ein bereirah, so he's not going to
be impressed by the last case, and for him it's obvious that
the last case is not valid, so it's not a ריח הגט
rei'ach hagget problem.
Okay. ואזדא רבי יוחנן לטעמיה דאמר רבי אסי אמר רבי יוחנן האחין
שחלקו לקוחות
הן ומחזירין זה לזה ביובל. ve'azda Rabbi Yochanan leta'ameih de'amar Rabbi Assi
amar Rabbi Yochanan ha'achin shechalaku lekuchot hen umachzirin zeh lazeh beyovel. Okay,
they are purchasers and it all returns in the יובל, yovel, so
he basically holds אין ברירה, ein bereirah, and since he holds it
in general, he's not going to be bothered by the case in
the משנה mishnah even to be a ריח הגט rei'ach hagget problem.
וצריכא. utzricha. And you need to tell me in both cases: the
case of inheritance and the case in the משנה. mishnah. אי אתמר
בהא, ei itmar beha, if it was said in the case of
the
משנה, mishnah, בהא קאמר רבי יוחנן דאין ברירה משום דבעינא לשמה. beha
ka'amar Rabbi Yochanan de'ein bereirah mishum deba'ina lishmah. That's not just רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, everybody might hold the case in the משנה mishnah
you can't get to choose later because the law requirement might be
a special demand that you need to make have it in mind
concretely at the time whatever your general ברירה bereirah position is. אבל
התם, aval hatam, but in the case by the inheritance, מכר הוא
דאמר רחמנא ליהדר ביובל אבל ירושה ומתנה לא. mecher hu de'amar Rachmana
lihadar beyovel aval yerusha umattanah lo. The תורה Torah is saying that
a real sale goes back at the
יובל, yovel, but things that are inherited or gift are not. And
since this went through a path of inheritance, you know, whatever you
hold about ברירה, bereirah, you know, maybe it would actually not be
a יובל yovel problem. ואי אשמועינן שדה, ve'ei ashmi'inan sadeh, if you
just told us that there's an idea of אין ברירה ein bereirah
by the field, okay, so that's very clear then. He's really holding
אין ברירה. ein bereirah. So much that we treat it as a
normal sale. So okay, but that's משום דלחומרא, mishum delachumra, we're being
strict, we're saying give it back through the יובל. yovel. אי נמי
מעיקרא, ei nami me'ikara, or what we're saying is, you know, it's
אין ברירה ein bereirah because there actually was an original entity that
we can like restore it to. So maybe that's what we're supposed
to do during the יובל. yovel. Okay. אבל הכא אימא לא, aval
hacha eima lo, but here maybe to say so absolutely אין ברירה
ein bereirah that there's not even a ריח הגט rei'ach hagget problem—like
that's the point we made before. Wonderful, you hold אין ברירה. ein
bereirah. Doesn't tell us that the גט get *get* should not be
a ריח הגט *reiach haget* problem and shouldn't be maybe create a
perception that it's a good גט get *get*. So I might think
that here we would be strict and say that it creates a
perception of a good גט get *get*. צריכא *Sricha*, he's telling us
both. Okay, so there's one point which is whatever you hold about
ברירה breirah, *breira*, the case of the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah*'s okay because
it says לשמה lishma *lishma* and you have to know concretely when
it's being written that it's for that woman. Okay, but then the
question is what type of גיטין *gittin* create a perception that they're
good that would fall into this very you know this very hard
rabbinic category of ריח הגט *reiach haget* which is the worst of
both worlds. You've got a פסול pasul, *pasul* גט get *get*, you're
לא מגורשת *lo megureshet*, but it looks כשר *kosher* enough that we're
going to treat you as מגורשת *megureshet* for a כהן kohen, *kohen*.
Okay, and then you have a whole range of opinions from שמואל
*Shmuel* that basically says anytime we use the word פסול *pasul* it's
a ריח הגט *reiach haget* to an opinion that every case in
the משנה *Mishnah* except the first is a ריח הגט *reiach haget*
problem because it's not a visible problem so it is a problem.
To finally the case of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* that nothing is
a ריח הגט *reiach haget* problem, right, even the last case of
the משנה *Mishnah* which is only a
ברירה breirah *breira* problem and not visible, nothing is a ריח הגט
*reiach haget* problem. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* gets into the
סוגיא *sugya* of ברירה breirah *breira*. This is like the classic סוגיא
*sugya* of ברירה breirah, *breira*. So let's, one of the classic סוגיות
*sugyos*, let's take a look. בעי מיניה רב הושעיה מרבי יהודה *Ba'ei
minei Rav Oshaya mei-Rabbi Yehuda*. רב הושעיה *Rav Oshaya* asked רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda*. אמר ללבלר *Amar le-lavlar*, you said to the
סופר *sofer*, כתוב לאיזה שתצא בפתח תחילה *Kesov le-eizo she-teitzei be-pesach techila*.
Write the גט get *get* for the one for you know the
wife which is going to walk out of the door first.
This is like the יפתח Yiftach *Yiftach* גט get *get*.
The יפתח *Yiftach* גט get. *get*, exactly, exactly. He'll be the קרבן
*korban*.
Just like the נזיר
*nazir*. Yeah, exactly, which is also like a יפתח *Yiftach* story, exactly.
So it's not the wife I'll decide on later, both my wives
have the same name, the wife that walks out of the door
first that'll be the one it's written for. Maybe that's better than
the one that I will decide. And this is what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is going to call the difference between תולה בדעת עצמו
toleh bedaas atzmo. *tola be-da'at atzmo* and תולה בדעת אחרים toleh bedaas
acherim, *tola be-da'at acherim*. If I say write it for the wife
I'll decide as רש״י *Rashi* sort of says you're showing that you're
פוסח על שתי הסעיפים *pose'ach al shtei ha-se'ifim*. רש״י *Rashi* uses a
nice phrase from תנ״ך *Tanach*. You're jumping between the two doorsteps. Like
it shows that you are like you know you can't make up
your mind. Okay, so there's no ברירה breirah. *breira*, it means when
you're writing it you're indecisive. So we can't say oh retrospectively we
see you had this wife in mind. You couldn't have made up
your mind then and you didn't so what you had in mind
then was was that you didn't was that you hadn't didn't have
anything in mind. You were conflicted, you were indecisive. Okay, whereas if
I say תולה בדעת אחרים Toleh bedaas acherim, *tola be-da'at acherim*, no,
I have totally made up my mind. You know which one I
want to divorce? The one who walks out of the door first.
Okay, I'm not indecisive. I am a hundred percent certain. I don't
know who that one is, but I'm a hundred percent certain that
that is the wife I want to divorce. Okay, like let's say
you said, you know, something else. The you know the first one
who serves me a bad meal. Okay, so I've made up my
mind. I don't want to be married to the wife who serves
me a bad meal and we'll determine who it is based on
the first one who whatever. Okay, so okay. So that's not a
question of being indecisive and maybe therefore ברירה breira. *breira* will work.
Okay, so that's his question. If you said the first one who
goes out of the door will that work? Okay.
So the סופר *sofer* doesn't have to have any לשמה *lishma* in
mind so to speak? It's just the סופר *sofer* that has to
write. Correct, correct.
I mean, yes, basically that's correct. I mean how would that work?
Like he does have to I mean the סופר *sofer*'s לשמה *lishma*
is based on the husband's.
No, but I'm going to know these are my wives' names שרה
ורבקה *Sarah ve-Rivka*.
No, no, no, no, they both have the same name.
Let's say they didn't.
Then this can't work because it won't have the right name in
the גט get.
*get*. It will, and it says alright these are my wives' names
and the סופר *sofer* the husband goes away, he doesn't even know,
the סופר *sofer* finds out.
Oh, it got determined before it was written? Oh, that would totally
be okay. No, no, this is while it's being written the what
nobody has walked out of the door yet. It's still a ברירה
breira *breira* case.
No, but but the husband doesn't even have to know. In other
words you can empower a סופר *sofer* you go flip a coin,
right?
Yeah, yeah, I understand your question, I understand your question. Yes, that's
correct. Okay, but anyway this case is is that while it's being
written it's still not determined. That's why it's a לשמה *lishma* problem.
לאיזה שתצא בפתח תחילה מהו *Le-eizo she-teitzei be-pesach techila mahu*. אמר ליה
Amar lei, תניתוה *Amar lei tanituha*. We taught in the משנה *Mishnah*.
הכותב אמר ללבלר כתוב לאיזה שארצה אגרש בו פסול לגרש בו *Ha-kotev
amar le-lavlar ketov le-eizo she-ertzeh agaresh bo pasul le-garesh bo*. אלמא אין
ברירה breira *Alma ein breira*. Look it doesn't work when you say
I'll decide later. So he did not realize the difference between תולה
בדעת עצמו tola b'daas atzmo *tola be-da'at atzmo* and תולה בדעת אחרים
tola b'daas acheirim. *tola be-da'at acherim*. He thought it's all the same,
ברירה breira. *breira*, so it doesn't work. So גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says
איתיביה *Eitiveih*, I'll ask you on this. האומר לבניו הריני שוחט את
הפסח על מי שיעלה מכם ראשון לירושלים *Ha-omer le-vanav ha-reini shochet et
ha-Pesach al mi she-ya'aleh mikem rishon li-Yerushalayim*. I'll slaughter the קרבן פסח
*korban Pesach* for the first one of you that gets to ירושלים
*Yerushalayim* on ערב פסח *Erev Pesach*.
So and then he slaughtered the פסח *Pesach* and then the sons
started showing up. Like all you guys came late to שיעור *shiur*.
Okay, so כיון *keivan* שנכנס ראשון ראשו ורובו זכה בחלקו *keivan she-nichnas
rishon rosho ve-rubo zachah be-chelko*. So even though it was already slaughtered,
as soon as the first one comes in the door retrospectively it
turns out that he was the one it was slaughtered for. That
how is it determined? The guy who first enters himself his head
and his majority, you know, into into ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. Okay, now not
only that ומזכה את אחיו עמו *u-mezakeh et echav imo*. But once
he gets retroactively included in the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach*, all of
his brothers get included through him. We'll see how that works in
a moment. So anyway we'll see how that works in a moment.
Anyway you see יש ברירה yesh breira. *yesh breira*, that's like the
first one who walks out of the door. And of course the
funny thing is is that maybe it's not the same לשמה *lishma*
requirement there. It doesn't say לא לשמה *lo lishma*. You have to
be included, but maybe there's not the same לא *lo* demand. Here
in this סוגיא *sugya*, what should be pointed out is, as opposed
to the line we just said a minute ago, this סוגיא *sugya*
assumes that there's not a special higher demand of גט get, *get*
based on the word of לא *lo*, לשמה *lishma*. That whatever normally
works for ברירה breira. *breira* could work for גט get? *get*. It
doesn't treat גט get *get* as something special. So it says look,
if ברירה breira *breira* works by שחט *shechting* the קרבן פסח *Korban
Pesach*, it should work here by it should work here by the
גט get *get*, the first wife that walks out the door. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אמר ליה *amar lei*, so he said
back to him, הושעיא ברי *Hoshaya beri*, הושעיא *Hoshaya* my son, וכי
פוסחים אצל גיטין *vechi pesachim etzel gittin*? What's the comparison? הא איתמר
*ha itmar*, why is it not comparable? כי איתמר לה אמר רבי
יוחנן *ki itmar la amar Rabbi Yochanan*, why is it not comparable?
כדי לזרזן במצוה *kedei lezarzen bemitzvah*, because the case of שחט *shechting*
קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach*, it's not real ברירה breira *breira*. Okay, it's
not really like I haven't decided which son it's going to be
for, and it's only going to be for the son that gets
here first. I am שחט *shechting* the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach* for
my all my whole family. So why did I say I'm doing
it for the one who gets here first? I was trying to
get them moving along. It's ערב פסח *Erev Pesach* and they're still
not here in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. Okay, so I'm trying to get them
to be you know to encourage them to be a little more
alacrity, but ultimately it's not ברירה breira *breira*. Ultimately I have in
mind all of them. Okay, how do you know that? That's not
what it sounds like. So דיקא נמי דקתני *deika nami d'katani*, כיון
שנכנס ראשון ראשו ורובו זכה בחלקו ומזכה אחיו עמו *keivan shenichnas rishon
rosho verubo zakah bechelko umezakeh echav imo*. No, you can figure it
out because how did the other brothers get included? I said I'm
only doing it for the one who shows up first. And he
comes after it's been שחט *shechted*, and not only does he get
included retroactively, but they do. Even if he wanted to have them
share his portion, that can only happen after that's only happening after
the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach* is שחט
*shechted*. It's too late to include people in your portion after it's
been שחט *shechted*. So how does it work that the other brothers
get to be a part of it? So אי אמרת בשלמא דאמנינהו
מעיקרא *ei amart bishlama d'amninehu me'ikara*, if you originally he included everybody,
שפיר *shapir*, then it works. אלא אי אמרת דאמנינהו לאחר שחיטה *ela
ei amart d'amninehu le'achar shechita*,
but if the if the brother who became included only included his
fellow brothers after it was שחט *shechted*, after he showed up in
ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, so מי קא מיתמנו *mi ka mitmanu*? How do they
get you know accounted in the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach*? והתנן נמנין
ומושכין ידיהן מהן עד שישחט *vehatnan nimnin umoshchin yadeihen mehen ad sheyishachat*.
So the fact that the other brothers get included show that it
was never really up in the air that who was going to
be part of the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach*. He was always שחט
*shechting* the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach* for everybody. Okay. תניא נמי הכי
*tanya nami hachi*, and it's similar, מעשה שקדמו בנות לבנים *ma'aseh shekadmu
banot lebanim*. One time the daughters came to ירושלים *Yerushalayim* before the
sons when a father did this. ונמצאו בנות זריזות *venimtze'u banot zerizot*,
and it turned out that the daughters were the ones who showed
real like alacrity for the מצוה *mitzvah*, ובנים שפלים *ubanim shefalim*, and
the sons were שלעפערס *schleppers*. Okay, so what is that relevant? It's
relevant cause it doesn't say that the sons didn't get to be
part of the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach*. It just says it turned
out that they were the שלעפערס *schleppers*. So the whole point of
this is to show who's the person that has זריזות *zerizus* and
who's a שלעפער *schlepper*, but it's not that they actually would get
excluded from the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach*. Okay. So you can't prove
it from the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach* story. Anyway, so we basically
have that the question was raised about תולה בדעת אחרים tola b'daas
acheirim. *toleh bedaat acherim*, and the answer was, oh, that's no good
cause תולה בדעת עצמו tola b'daas atzmo, *toleh bedaat atzmo* is no
good. So אביי Abaye *Abaye* points out that that misses the point,
that that answer ignored a potential difference between those two categories. So
אמר אביי *amar Abaye*, אביי *Abaye* said, I don't get it, so
אמר אביי *amar Abaye* said, כבעי מיניה תולה בדעת אחרים tola b'daas
acheirim *kiba'ei minei toleh bedaat acherim*. He wanted to know a question
of ברירה breira? *breira* when it was dependent on how somebody else
would act, which wife would walk out first. Okay. וקפשיט ליה תולה
בדעת עצמו tola b'daas atzmo. *ufashet lei toleh bedaat atzmo*. And he
says, oh, I'll prove it to you cause when you're indecisive and
you haven't made up your mind yet it doesn't work. That's not
relevant. Okay. והדר מותיב ליה תולה בדעת אחרים tola b'daas acheirim? *vehadar
motiv lei toleh bedaat acherim*, then he finally got back to the
case of the דעת אחרים da'at acherim *daat acherim* by the קרבן
פסח *Korban Pesach* which actually was a relevant case. But what he's
obviously mixing it up, he thinks that they're all in the same
conversation. Obviously the point is that there could be a difference. That
תולה בדעת אחרים acherim *toleh bedaat acherim*, the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach*
case and the wife that would walk out first, those are relevant
examples. Okay, those are cases where maybe ברירה breira. *breira* does work.
תולה בדעת עצמו tola b'daas atzmo *toleh bedaat atzmo* is maybe a
case where it doesn't. How do you think that you know how
why are you having them in the same conversation? So so the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said and then again just to show you the
רש״י *Rashi*, it's great רש״י *Rashi*. He says like this. If you
look at רש״י *Rashi*, it's four lines before the lines get wide.
He says דילמא dilma תולה בדעת עצמו לית לן ברירה breira *dilma
toleh bedaat atzmo leit lan breira*, maybe when it's you yourself are
going to decide later there's no ברירה breira. *breira*. דמידא תולה *demida
toleh*. since you made a stipulation I'll decide later, גילה בדעתו שהיה
פוסח על שתי הספין you were jumping between the two doorsteps you
couldn't make up your mind. ולגמרי מהוה. v'lagemrei mava. You can't say
oh retroactively when you decide later it shows that that was what
you were thinking then. No, obviously what I was thinking then was
that I hadn't made up my mind. Okay? But this one, when
you say based on which wife comes out of the door, גמר
בדעתו מעיקרא לזו שתצא, gamar b'da'ato m'ikara l'zo she'teitzei, I have completely
made up my mind. I want a divorce for the wife that
comes out of the door first. Okay? I don't know who it
is, but I've made up my mind. All right, anyway so the
גמרא says like this, wait one minute. So he says, so אביי
said I don't understand why he thought that those were what were
relevant to one another. Those are clearly different cases. Clearly his whole
question was that תלה בדעת אחרים tala b'da'at acherim might be a
different case. So אמר רבא, amar Rava, so רבא Rava said back,
מה קושיא, ma kushya, why is it difficult? דילמא maybe דמאן דאית
ליה ברירה, d'man d'is lei breirah, maybe the רב אושעיא Rav Oshaya
thought that, I think it was רב אושעיא Rav Oshaya who answered
anyway, maybe he thought that his whole point of his answer was
that he didn't accept that there was a difference. Okay? He assumed
that if you hold ברירה, breira לא שנא תלה בדעת עצמו ולא
שנא תלה בדעת אחרים אית ליה ברירה, lo shna tala b'da'at atzmo
v'lo shna tala b'da'at acherim is lei breirah, then you'll hold about
it across the board. ומן דלית ליה ברירה, u'man d'leit lei breirah,
and if you don't hold about it, לא שנא תלה בדעת עצמו
ולא שנא תלה בדעת אחרים לית ליה ברירה, lo shna tala b'da'at
atzmo v'lo shna tala b'da'at acherim leit lei breirah, then you, if
you don't hold about it, you don't hold about it across the
board. He says you're right, the questioner who said is it different
if the wife walks out of, if I say about the wife
that walks out of the door, thought there might be a difference
between those two categories. But the responder who said no it's based
on our משנה, maybe his whole point was to deny the legitimacy
of making a distinction between those two categories. Okay? But either way,
that clearly is the issue on the table. Will it, is it
possible that it makes a difference that it could work even for
a גט get even with the לשמה requirement, maybe it ברירה breira,
works better in a case of תלה בדעת אחרים tala b'da'at acherim
as opposed to תלה בדעת עצמו? tala b'da'at atzmo? So we still
don't have an answer to that. That's the question on the table.
You had a question David? I'm not sure if this is answered
there or not, but in the case of the sons the father
told the children, so they're making a decision right? Right. In the
case of the wives, she didn't make a decision. Right so it's,
so you're right, it's less תלה בדעת אחרים tala b'da'at acherim as
much as it is תלה באחרים. tala b'acherim. The real problem is
when you're תלה בדעת עצמו, tala b'da'at atzmo, the one I will
pick later, it undermines the ability of ברירה breira because as רש"י
Rashi says you're indecisive now. So our ability to say that later
it turns out that's what you meant, right? What do you mean?
If you had not, it was clear that at the time you
actually had not made up your mind. So it's really תלה בדעת
עצמו tala b'da'at atzmo as opposed to תלה באחרים. tala b'acherim. Whether
it's דעת daas אחרים acherim or מעשה אחרים, ma'aseh acherim, it's תלה
בדעת עצמו tala b'da'at atzmo as opposed to תלה באחרים. tala b'acherim.
Okay? All right. We really have to look at what he says.
For some reason, let's say he says I want you to write
a גט get for the first person to walk out of my
house and it turns out to be his son. Did you like
do, write a גט get again? Well right, well that's the יפתח
story. Okay anyway right. So the גמרא says like this. Okay, so
this is the question. Will it matter? אמר ליה רב משרשיא לרבא,
amar lei Rav Mesharshaya l'Rava, והא רבי יהודה דתלה בדעת עצמו לית
ליה ברירה ותלה בדעת אחרים אית ליה ברירה. v'ha Rabbi Yehuda d'tala
b'da'at atzmo leit lei breirah v'tala b'da'at acherim is lei breirah. So
רבא Rava said no, maybe we'll pick a position that that's not
a legitimate distinction. So now we're going to show no, it is
a legitimate distinction. רב משרשיא Rav Mesharshaya says to רבא, Rava, רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, who in a case of תלה בדעת עצמו tala
b'da'at atzmo he doesn't hold of ברירה, breira and in the case
of תלה בדעת אחרים tala b'da'at acherim he does hold of ברירה.
breira, Where do you know this? תלה בדעת עצמו לית ליה ברירה
דתניא, tala b'da'at atzmo leit lei breirah d'tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא. Baraita. הלוקח יין מבין הכותים, halokeiach yayin mibein ha'Kutim, you're buying
wine from Samaritans. Now when you buy, this is the case is
it's ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, it's maybe it's בין השמשות bein hashmashot
even, okay, and you do not have time to be מפריש תרומות
ומעשרות. mafrish trumot u'ma'asrot. All right now, if you are dealing with
דמאי demai grain brought or whatever from an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz,
you're allowed to be מפריש תרומות ומעשרות mafrish trumot u'ma'asrot during בין
השמשות. bein hashmashot. But if you've bought it from a Samaritan the
assumption is that they're וודאי vadai not מפריש תרומות ומעשרות. mafrish trumot
u'ma'asrot. Actually תוספות Tosafot says maybe they וודאי vadai are for if
they're eating it themselves, but if they're selling it to other people
they're וודאי vadai not. So you're וודאי חייב בתרומות ומעשרות. vadai chayav
b'trumot u'ma'asrot. There's only a problem is that you don't really have
time to be מפריש, mafrish, okay, or maybe it's even בין השמשות
bein hashmashot and you're not allowed to do a real הפרשה. hafrasha.
Okay, so here's what you have to do. Okay, so what you
do is you say the following. אומר שני לוגים שאני עתיד להפריש,
omeir shnei lugim she'ani atid l'hafrish, will assume for argument's sake that
there are a hundred and two לוג log of the that you
bought. So two of them are תרומה truma because you normally give
about two percent for תרומה. truma. הרי הן תרומה, harei hen truma,
that's how you know it's not דמאי demai because דמאי demai you
don't have to give תרומה truma you assume תרומה truma was given.
Here you assume nothing was given. Okay so two לוג log are
תרומה. truma. Which two לוג? log? I don't know. The two לוג
log to be identified later. I don't have time right now to
start measuring things out. I'm going to drink a lot of wine
over שבת, Shabbat, maybe I'll even drink half of it, but I'll
leave enough over so that after שבת Shabbat I can identify where.
which was the stuff that was תרומה, terumah, which was the stuff
that was מעשר maaser and so on. I just don't have time
to do any of that right now. Okay, so the two לוג
log that I'm going to separate after שבת Shabbos will be תרומה.
terumah. עשרה מעשר ראשון, asarah maaser rishon, ten will be of the
remaining hundred will be מעשר ראשון. maaser rishon. Okay, תשעה מעשר שני,
tisha maaser sheni, nine of the remaining ninety will be מעשר שני,
maaser sheni, right? That's ten percent of the remaining. ומיחל ושותה מיד.
umechal veshoteh miyad. Now רש''י Rashi says מיחל mechal means is that
you transfer your מחלל mechallel the מעשר שני maaser sheni on money.
תוספות Tosafos says you don't do that because since you have not
identified what yet is the מעשר שני, maaser sheni, you can't yet
do the, you can't do the חילול, chillul, you can't transfer the
value onto the money. So תוספות Tosafos just says ומיחל ושותה מיד.
umechal veshoteh miyad. He has two explanations. One means ומוה ושותה מיד,
umoveh veshoteh miyad, you mix the wine and you drink it right
away, or מתחיל ושותה מיד. matchil veshoteh miyad. תוספות Tosafos anyway does
not give a lot of weight to the word ומיחל. umechal. He
just means you begin to drink immediately, although רש''י Rashi says it
means you redeem the מעשר maaser before you begin. Okay, did you
have a question, Dena? No. Okay, fine. דברי רבי מאיר, Divrei Rabbi
Meir, that's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So basically רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
holds יש ברירה. yesh breira? You're saying now you're separating it. Your
words are designating which barrels of wine have you designated, TBD. Okay,
but you've done the act of המפריש hamaphrish which the barrels to
be identified later. דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי יהודה ורבי
יוסי ורבי שמעון אוסרין, Rabbi Yehuda veRabbi Yose veRabbi Shimon osrin, רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
say no, that doesn't work. So you see they don't hold ברירה.
breira. Now that's תולה בדעת עצמו. That's something that it's not ברירה
breira because you're totally in control and you're deferring the other half
of your decision till later. Now it could be here you didn't
have time, it wasn't because you were conflicted, but nevertheless it's not
you, you could have made, you know, you are pushing off your
own decision, half of your decision to later. That's לית ליה ברירה.
lais lei breira. Now תולה בדעת אחרים אית ליה ברירה, toleh bedaas
acherim is lei breira, but they hold of ברירה breira, when it's
תולה בדעת אחרים, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda does. How do you know
that? תנן. Tnan. מהי באותן ימים? mahi baosun yamim? A man gives
a גט get to his wife and says this will be your
גט get if I do not, if I don't recover from this
illness. He's on his, he's, you know, he's, he's maybe on his
deathbed, he has a very severe illness. He says, this'll be your
גט get if I don't recover from this illness. Now what is
her status during the interim? If it worked retroactively, right? So what's
her status? Does she treat herself during that period as still married
or as divorced? Now doesn't mean like does she sleep with other
men, but can she eat תרומה terumah for example if she's married
to a כהן, you know? What's her status during that, because we
don't know whether retroactively she will be married or divorced based on
whether or not he recovers or not. So מהי באותן ימים? mahi
baosun yamim? רבי יהודה אומר הרי היא כאשת איש לכל דבריה. Rabbi
Yehuda omer harei hi keishes ish lechol devareha. She's an אשת איש
eishes ish for all matters because she has to treat herself as,
that maybe he won't, maybe he'll survive and it won't be a
גט. get But nevertheless says the גמרא, וכי מית הוי גיטא, vechi
meis havei gitta, but when he dies it will be a גט.
get Now what does that prove about יש ברירה? yesh breira That
since if he dies it's a גט, get it shows יש ברירה
yesh breira? that retroactively it was a גט? get That's just a
תנאי. tnai. Isn't that a תנאי? tnai? You make a condition and
there's a million conditions. Since when is that יש ברירה? yeish breira
This is your גט get if this happens. תולה בדעת אחרים, although
this is regarding himself. Well it's, right, first of all that's interesting.
There's, no, as the way I think תוספות Tosafos says or רש''י
Rashi says, no, the אחרים here is God. The אחרים is מי
שהחיים והמוות תלויים בידו. mi shehachayim vehamaves tluyim beyado. So it's like
it's not a decision that you have to make. Okay, but anyway
so תוספות, Tosafos, רש''י Rashi has a complicated explanation about why this
תנאי tnai is a type of ברירה. breira But תוספות Tosafos actually
says the easiest thing. תוספות Tosafos says, I don't know how to
turn this off because of my stupid phone, anyway, cause תוספות Tosafos
says that no, here's the point and here's why we said מהי
באותן ימים. mahi baosun yamim. The reason that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says she's considered an אשת איש eishes ish during that period is
not because it's a ספק safek whether he'll die or not. It's
because רבי יהודה reads when he says, this is your גט לכשימות
lichshayamus when I die, if and when I die, that the way
we interpret those words are, not it is your גט as of
today if I die. This is your גט when I die. Of
course when you die, when, right he didn't say מעכשיו meachshav or
maybe he did, but it's going to be how we're going to
interpret it. When I die it's a little too late, you're already
dead. So he interprets the word when I die meaning a minute
before I die. And that's why she's an אשת איש eishes ish
כל אותן ימים, kol osun yamim, because even if he does die
the גט only takes effect at the last minute. So then here's
the question though: which minute does the גט take effect? You're giving
a גט now to take effect at what time exactly? Oh, the
minute before I die. Well what time is that? I don't know,
it'll be determined later. So you are defining the effect of a
גט to take place at a time, it's not a condition, right?
There's no condition being made. The time it's going to take effect
is, let's say I say this גט will take effect, you know,
on the day that the, that the Cubs win the World Series.
Okay, so, so that's not a condition. I mean maybe eventually you
know, so the Cubs did recently win the World Series, no? Oh
okay but they almost did. So maybe in a, given enough time,
whatever, it will happen, okay? So it's not a condition. It's a
definite גט to take effect at that time. So what. is that
time is to be determined later, that's a תוספות Tosafos type of
a ברירה. breira. It's not conditional, it's defining, the same way you're
defining the barrels of wine that are תרומה terumah and מעשרות, ma'asros,
it's defining the time that the גט is effective, and that is
a ברירה type of a case. Okay? So there you see, it
works, יש ברירה when it's תולה בדעת אחרים. So you see that
that distinction holds. אמר ליה רב משרשיא לרבא. Amar lei Rav Mesharshiya
l'Rava. So that was one proof that there's a distinction between תולה
בדעת עצמו and תולה בדעת אחרים. Everybody's jumping on רבא Rava now.
Said רב משרשיא לרבא, Rav Mesharshiya l'Rava, הרי רבי שמעון, harei Rabbi
Shimon, I'll give you another case, רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, דתולה בדעת
עצמו לית ליה ברירה, dtola b'daas atzmo leis lei breira, he doesn't
hold of ברירה by תולה בדעת עצמו, ובתולה בדעת אחרים אית ליה
ברירה, uv'tola b'daas acheirim is lei breira, but when it's תולה בדעת
אחרים he does hold of it. How do you know it? תולה
בדעת עצמו לית ליה ברירה, Tola b'daas atzmo leis lei breira, הך
דאמרן. hach d'amran. He doesn't hold of it, that was that case
about the wine, that he says you can't take the wine to
be determined later. That doesn't work. Okay? That was a case of
תולה בדעת עצמו. You hadn't yourself finished the thing. Okay. הך דאמרן.
Hach d'amran. תולה בדעת אחרים אית ליה ברירה, Tola b'daas acheirim is
lei breira, where does he hold of ברירה by תולה בדעת אחרים?
דתניא, Detanya, הריני בועליך על מנת שירצה אבא. Hareini bo'alaich al mnas
sheyirtzeh Abba. A guy says to a woman, I'm, we'll have sex
together, and this sex will count as קידושין, kiddushin, ביאה bias is
one of the ways to do קידושין, kiddushin, if your dad's okay
with it. All right? So אף על פי, af al pi, we're
having sex either way, but it counts as קידושין kiddushin if your
dad's okay with it. So אף על פי שלא רצה אב מקודשת.
af al pi shelo ratzah av mekudeshes. The first opinion is she's
מקודשת mekudeshes even if the father's not okay. Why? Because of the
principle of אין אדם עושה בעילתו בעילת זנות, ein adam oseh beilaso
beilas znus, that you're assuming the father will be okay, and we
know deep down you would not want sex to be taking place
outside of the context of marriage. So therefore, we're going to assume
that you really are not making it dependent on that condition. You
really want it to be a קידושין kiddushin regardless. That's the first
opinion. רבי שמעון בן יהודה אומר משום רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon ben
Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Shimon, no. רצה אב מקודשת, ratzah av mekudeshes,
no, it's like he said. If the father wants, she's מקודשת. mekudeshes.
לא רצה אב אינה מקודשת, lo ratzah av einah mekudeshes, it's not.
Now, again, that sounds just like a condition. Why is that a
case of ברירה? Okay, that's not clear why that's a ברירה. That
sounds like a straight condition. So here it might have to do
with the idea of קידושי ביאה. kiddushei biah. That קידושי ביאה, kiddushei
biah, as opposed to all the other forms of קידושין, kiddushin, it
could be that קידושי ביאה kiddushei biah is more that marriage gets
created automatically even without intent for marriage, as long as it's done
in a marital context. It's more like the reality of living together
as husband and wife, like a common law marriage, creates, this is
a very relevant למעשה l'maaseh by a case about when the קידושין
kiddushin was פסול, can we say that the woman doesn't need a
גט or do we say that the fact that they were still
living together as husband and wife even without intent that it should
create a marriage, the reality itself, that's what קידושי ביאה kiddushei biah
is, the reality of having sex as a married couple itself defines
the marriage. So if you say that latter way, then it doesn't
matter what your דעת daas is. Well, that's a big מחלוקת הפוסקים
ואחרונים. machlokes haposkim v'achronim. If you say that way, it doesn't matter
what his דעת is. What really matters is was it a marital
context or not? But not like, but you can't make it a
stipulation, if this and this happens then I want it to take
effect. The question is what was the nature of the, what was
the context? What was the nature of the way in which the
act has taken place? Not, and a normal תנאי tnai wouldn't work.
So that's why the גמרא could say that's a ברירה issue. A
תנאי tnai doesn't work by קידושי ביאה. kiddushei biah. A, right? A
תנאי tnai means it's taking effect because I get to determine and
define, like do I want it to take effect or not. Here
you don't get to decide if you want it. It just automatically
becomes a marriage if it's done in the context of marriage. Well,
was it a marital context or not a marital context? When you
were having sex, were you having it as a type of זנות,
znus, or were you having it as a marital context? If that's
the question we ask, not what was your תנאי, tnai, but we
ask what was the context, was it a זנות znus context or
a marriage context? We say well, that was going to depend on
whether what the father was going to be okay with. So that's
already more of a ברירה. Based on what the father says, that
ability to redefine the context of the act, that's not a תנאי
tnai issue. That's a ברירה issue. So that's how the גמרא understands
it. So it says look, here's another case, דתולה בדעת עצמו לית
ליה ברירה dtola b'daas atzmo leis lei breira by the wine, ובתולה
בדעת אחרים אית ליה ברירה uv'tola b'daas acheirim is lei breira by
the father's agreement retroactively defining the context of this act of sex.
So, so here we have all this good evidence that it does
make a difference. So אמר ליה, so רבא's Rava response to both
of those arguments is, בין לרבי יהודה בין לרבי שמעון לא שנא
תולה בדעת עצמו ולא שנא תולה בדעת אחרים אית ליה ברירה. bein
l'Rabbi Yehuda bein l'Rabbi Shimon lo shna tola b'daas atzmo v'lo shna
tola b'daas acheirim is lei breira. He got it back, רבא, Rava,
consistent. No, I reject that. Both, everybody holds of ברירה, that's why
it works by the father, that's why it works by the, this
is a גט a minute before I die, they hold of ברירה
and they would hold of ברירה in a תולה בדעת עצמו case
as well. So what's the problem with the wine? Why did they
say you can't do the wine case? Okay? דהתם כדקתני טעמא. D'hasam
k'd'kasni ta'ama. The reason you can't do the wine case is because
it tells you the reason. In the end, אמרו לו, amru lo,
they said לרבי מאיר, l'Rabbi Meir, אי אתה מודה שמא יבקע הנוד.
ee atah modeh shema yibaka hanod. ונמצא שותה טבלים למפרע? venimtza shoteh
tvalim lemafrea? They said to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, in principle, you're
right. You could do it because of ברירה, but there's a big
concern. What happens if all the wine spills? Okay, this only works
if you actually leave over wine at the end. If something happens
and the wine barrels break, right, and all the wine spills, you
never retrospectively would have taken תרומות trumos and מעשרות maasros and you
would have been eating טבל. tevel. So that's why we've got a
problem. Okay, now of course everybody else held that they were just
saying that to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir לשיטתו. leshitaso. Real fundamentally it
doesn't work, but you should at least be concerned that the wine
will spill. But רבא Rava said no, they agreed in principle you
could do ברירה. They were just saying we're not going to let
you do this because it'll because you could wind up it'll be
a disaster. And what does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say? אמר להם,
amar lahem, he said to them, לכשיבקע, lichsheyibaka, when it breaks, so
I'll worry about it. Okay, which is okay, maybe it'll happen, but
I'm not going to worry about it, which is so funny because
normally רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir חייש למיעוטא chaish lemiutei anyway. So רבא
Rava holds you either hold of ברירה across the board or you
don't. Okay, and the reason they didn't hold of it by the
wine was not because they don't hold of ברירה, it's because they
were afraid the wine would spill. And the other approach is, actually
it makes a big difference. Maybe we say ברירה when it's not
about you making up your mind, but when you haven't yet made
up your mind or you haven't finished your own act, maybe that's
a particular reason to say that we don't say ברירה.